Leah: Physical bullying, is the
most obvious form of bullying and
physical bullies, usually tend
to be bigger, stronger, and more
aggressive than their targets.
They use physical attacks like
kicking, hitting, punching and shoving.
Physical bullying is the easiest to
identify and most likely, what people
think of when they think of bullying
as this receives more attention from
schools than other more subtle forms.
Rhiannon: Verbal bullying uses
words, and name-calling to gain
power and control over a victim,
relentlessly insulting
and belittling them.
This is often based on the way a child
or young person looks or acts and
is often directed towards those with
disabilities or special educational needs.
Verbal bullying almost always occurs,
when adults aren’t around and when
victims do speak out, they are told to
‘ignore it’ but they should be listened
to, as it can leave deep emotional scars.
Leah: Emotional bullying is
sneaky and insidious and often
goes unnoticed by parents and
teachers.
It is often used by young
adolescents to ruin their target’s
social standing, by spreading
rumours, or breaking confidences.
This type of bullying is
most often used by girls.
Rhiannon: Cyberbullying is
bullying via the Internet, using a
smartphone, or other technology to
harass, threaten, embarrass,
or target another person.
It often involves the posting of
hurtful images, online threats,
and sending offensive or
discriminatory emails or texts.
Technology makes cyberbullies feel
anonymous and detached from the situation
whilst enabling them to target others
anytime, even in their own homes.
Leah: Sexual Bullying can
involve, sexual name-calling,
crude comments, vulgar gestures,
uninvited touching, sexual propositioning,
and use of pornographic materials.
In extreme cases, it can
lead to sexual assault.
Girls are most often the target
of this, but they can be targeted
both by boys and other girls.
‘Sexting’ [texts with sexual content]
also can lead to sexual bullying.
If a girl sends a photo of herself to a
boyfriend, he may, in anger share that
photo publicly if they break up and
contrary to her wishes or intentions.
Rhiannon: Prejudicial bullying, is
based on prejudices children and young
people may have towards different
races, religions, or sexual orientation.
Often, this type of bullying is
severe and can lead to hate crimes.
Any time a child is bullied for
their sexual orientation, race, or
religion, it should be reported.
Leah: The motivation of bullies, are
all different and not all bullies
will fit neatly into a category.
Some bullies will fall into several
categories and some may appear to
be in a category all their own.
Rhiannon: Some individuals become
bullies because they were once bullied
themselves and this is very common.
Others have big egos and a group of
followers and bully to keep their
Power or social standing.
Some bully out of jealousy and others
seem pleasant on the outside, but are
cold and calculating on the inside.
Leah: Bullies can also work
in groups or cliques, but when
they are on their own, behave
differently.
Some bullies are just totally indifferent
to the feelings of others and can
have deep psychological problems.
Rhiannon: Whatever the type of bully,
all bullying is wrong and should
not be tolerated, as it can have a
devastating effect on children and
young people's mental well-being.
It is something we should always be
mindful of and on the lookout for.